Register of the Commission for Polish Relief Records, 1939-1949
Hoover Institution Archives
Commission for Polish Relief Records,
1939-1949
48000
Commission for Polish Relief
70 manuscript boxes (29.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, reports, memoranda, financial records, and photographs, relating to efforts to provide relief to Poland during World War II. Also available on microfilm (52 reels).
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1948.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm (52 reels).
Access Points
Commission for Polish Relief; World War, 1939-1945; World War, 1939-1945--Civilian relief; World War, 1939-1945--Poland; Poland; United States--Foreign relations
Historical Note
In response to the appeal of the Polish Government in Exile -including the Prime Minister, General Wladyslaw Sikorski, and the Ambassador in Washington, Count Jerzy Potocki -we organized the Commission for Polish Relief, Inc., on September 25, 1939. The officers of the new organization were: Chauncey McCormick, Chairman; Maurice Pate, President. The Directors were Hugh Gibson, W. Hallam Tuck, Edgar Rickard, Perrin C. Galpin, Lewis L. Strauss, Theodore Abel, Frederic C. Walcott, and Mrs. Vernon Kellogg. They sacrificed important positions to answer this call of suffering. I was made Honorary Chairman of the Commission. It was my responsibility to conduct negotiations with the various governments concerned, to secure financial support, and enlist public support by making speeches and by issuing public statements. My colleagues attended to the major problems of purchase of supplies and transportation. For the Polish operations, a staff was quickly recruited in Europe by cable. Mr. William C. McDonald..., was located in Switzerland, enjoyed high confidence in Poland. He went to Berlin immediately to conduct negotiations with the Germans and then proceeded to Warsaw, where he set up arrangements for the distribution of food and medical-relief supplies. Mr. Gilbert Redfern... was recruited in London and sent promptly to Vilna, where he performed an outstanding task in carring for Polish refugees in the Baltic States. Mr. F. Dorsey Stephens, aided by his wife Zora, did equally devoted and useful work among the fifty thousand Polish refugees in France. In the New York headquarters of the Commission for Polish Relief, McCormick and Pate had the invaluable devotion and experienced work of Columba P. Murray, Jr., Colonel Joseph Krueger, and Bernard Fraser, all veterans of the American Relief Administration. Hugh Gibson and Frederic Walcott voluntarily gave generously of their time on the negotiating and diplomatic side. Mrs. Vernon Kellogg was a zealous raiser of private contributions in the United States... In the initiation of relief to Poland, we concentrated upon two programs: the supply of food and clothing to the underfed children in the congested districts and ghettos in Poland, and care of Polish refugees, now scattered over Europe. Mr. Pate set up canteens, under the care of Polish women, which provided special meals to 200,000 undernourished children and aged persons daily in Poland. The Polish Government in Exile had set up refugee relief, and our organization supplied it with food and clothing. Our route for shipments was from the United States to Sweden and thence to Hamburg or Danzig. When it was cut off because of the German invasion of Norway on April 9, 1940, the Commission was able to ship through Genoa or Lisbon and thence by rail to Poland. To finance the relief, the Commission supported the appeals of the Polish-American organizations in the United States, from whom we received about $400,000. The Polish Government in Exile made an initial donation of $186,225.
It was certain that if the Commission were to be successful in carrying out a substantial program, it would cost more than the combined resources of both charity appeals and the exiled Polish Government. Therefore, on February 29, 1940, I obtained a hearing before the House Foreign Affairs Committee and advocated a fifty-million-dollar appropriation to the Red Cross for relief for Poland. I urged Norman Davis, Chairman of the American Red Cross, to undertake this relief. When the Congressional appropriation subsequently became law, the Red Cross undertook medical aid, but our organization received no part of it for the major need: food. To stimulate charitable contributions, the Commission organized a mass meeting at New York City's Madison Square Garden on March 12 at which I spoke. It organized a mass meeting in Chicago at which I also spoke, and another in New York on April 28, where both General Joseph Haller, Minister of State of the Republic of Poland, and I spoke. In the meantime, August Zaleski, Minister of Foreign Affairs of the Polish Government in Exile in London, took a hand in the finances of the Relief Commission... Our total resources with these additions amounted to about $6,000,000, including $3,060,704 in Polish gold deposited in the National Bank of Rumania. We sent Dorsey Stephens to Bucharest to bring out the gold. The Bank of Rumania refused to hand it over. After all patience had been exhausted in negotiating with it, we attached its balances in New York and won our case on July 15, 1941, in the lower courts. Although the British blockade was in action against delivery of food to German-occupied territory, we had no difficulty in obtaining permits for relief shipments during the Chamberlain ministry. However, when Churchill succeeded Chamberlain as Prime Minister in May, 1940, he soon stopped all permits of food relief to Poland. At the outset of our Polish relief operations, I conducted negotiations with the Germans through their Embassy officials in Washington. They were most co-operative, and issued certificates of immunity from submarine attack, provided neutral vessels were used. After we were prevented by Mr. Churchill from sending overseas supplies to Poland, the Relief Commission deployed its American staff over Europe to seek food outside British control. They were able to make some purchases in the Baltic nations and in Russia, but in the end, the blockade closed in upon us, and this effort to aid Poland was ended. It was only by the incredible tenacity of Maurice Pate and our men in Europe that a meager stream of food and medical relief continued to trickle to Poland for nearly two more years. Beyond doubt, this saved thousands of lives. The further relief of Poland was now dependent on whether or not the British blockade could be relaxed for relief shipments. We did not abandon our effort to secure relaxation of the blockade, but merged this problem with those of the other small democracies.
Scope and Content of Collection
Correspondence, reports, memoranda, financial records, and photographs, relating to efforts to provide relief to Poland during World War II.
Container List
- Chairman's File, 1939-1941. (Box 1.)
  Speeches, addresses, statements, broadcast, press release, drafts, writings, telegrams, letters, memoranda, reports of meetings, telephone conversations and other records relating to CPR activity and food relief, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Cables (Box 1., Folder 1)
  - Clippings (Folder 2)
  - Correspondence. Includes memoranda, reports of meetings and telephone conversations
    - General (Folder 3)
    - Coulter J. L., Falconer J. I., Hobson A., McCollum E. V. (Folder 4)
    - Davison, Henry, 1918 (Folder 5)
      Relates to the Committee for Relief in Beligum and the Red Cross War Council
    - Galpin, Perrin (Folder 6)
    - Hartigan, John (Folder 7)
    - Krueger, Colonel (Folder 8)
    - McCormick, Chauncey (Folder 9)
    - Parke, Norman (Folder 10)
    - Pate, Maurice (Folder 11)
    - Richard, Edgar (Folder 12)
    - Richmond, Richard (Folder 13)
    - Sikorski, Wladyslaw (Folder 14)
    - Tuck, Hallam (Folder 15)
    - Tucker, Robert Leonard (Folder 16)
  - Speeches and writings
    - General
      - Correspondence and memoranda regarding CPR activity and food relief. Holograph and typescript (Folder 17)
      - Drafts of by-laws, membership lists (Folder 18)
    - Address, Polish mass meeting in the Chicago stadium, 1940 February 10. Typescript (Folder 19)
    - Address, Polish National Council of New York, New York City, New York, 1940 March 12. Typescript (Folder 20)
    - Speech, Finnish Pavilion, New York World's Fair, New York City, New York, 1940 May 16. Typescript (Folder 21)
    - Speech, Opening of Belgian Pavilion at New York World's Fair, New York City, New York, 1940 May 18. Typescript (Folder 22)
    - "We as Americans...," 1940 September. Statement. Typescript (Folder 23)
    - "America and the Famine in the Five Little Democracies," address, Vassar College, Poughkeepsie, New York, 1940 November 15. Press release (Folder 24)
    - "Feed Hungry Europe!" Collier's, 1940 November 23. Clipping (Folder 25)
    - "When Winter Comes to Europe," 1940 November 23. Typescript (Folder 26)
    - "The March of Hunger in Europe," address, Chicago, Illinois, 1941 February 16. Typescript (Folder 27)
    - "The Question of Peace," broadcast, National Broadcasting Company, New Haven, Connecticut, 1941 March 28. Press release (Folder 28)
    - "The Food Situation in Belgium as of July 1941." Typescript written by E. J. Bigwood with foreword by Herbert Hoover (Folder 29)
- Office File, 1939-1947. (Box 2.-6.)
  Reports, correspondence, lists, histories, legal documents, agreements, subscriptions, personnel records, press releases, radio broadcasts, publications, pamphlets and programs, arranged alphabetically by physical form. See also Chairman's File/Speeches and writings/General
  - General. Bound volume of various documents relating to operations of the CPR (Box 2., Folder 1)
  - By-laws (Folder 2)
  - Certificate of incorporation (Folder 3)
  - Correspondence regarding fund-raising needs (Folder 4)
  - Filing papers (Folder 5)
  - History of the organization. Includes some material about chronology of events in Poland (Folder 6-8)
  - Inquiries from Poles abroad regarding aid from CPR, fate of relatives in Poland, etc. (Box 3., Folder 1)
  - Lease (Folder 2)
  - Letterheads and envelopes of CPR (Folder 3)
  - License (Folder 4)
  - Liquidation papers (Folder 5)
  - Lists
    - Directors and officers (Folder 6)
    - Donations
      - 1939-1940 (Folder 7)
      - 1941 (Folder 8)
    - Mailing (Folder 9)
  - Personnel records (Box 4.)
    - Applications
      - General
        - 1940 (Folder 1)
        - 1941 (Folder 2)
      - Female
        - Secretary-Steno (Folder 3)
        - Miscellaneous (Folder 4)
      - Male
        - Foreign personnel
          - 1940 (Folder 5)
          - 1941 (Folder 6)
        - Fund raising (Folder 7)
        - Miscellaneous (Folder 8)
    - Correspondence between members of CPR and officers of various organizations, regarding recommendations (Box 5., Folder 1)
    - Decorations (Folder 2)
    - Lists (Folder 3)
    - Volunteer files (Folder 4)
  - Policy toward Poland (Folder 5)
  - Publicity material
    - General (Folder 6)
    - Clippings (Folder 7-10)
    - Pamphlets and programs (Folder 11)
    - Press releases (Box 6., Folder 1)
    - Publications
      - General (Folder 2)
      - News Bulletins (Folder 3)
    - Radio broadcasts (Folder 4)
  - Reports
    - 1940. Interim report of CPR (Folder 5)
    - 1945-1947. "Report on Organization and Operation of Mission in Poland" (Folder 6)
  - Subscriptions (Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous (Folder 8)
- Cables, 1940-1941. (Box 7.-11.)
  Telegrams arranged alphabetically by name of individual working on behalf of the organization
  - General (Box 7., Folder 1-2)
  - Brown, Lei and Paul Super (Bucharest) (Folder 3)
  - Exportkhleb (Soviet Union) (Folder 4-5)
  - Friar, Millard Shaler and Hallam Tuck (Brussels) (Folder 6)
  - Hansen C. K. (Denmark) (Folder 7)
  - Hartigan, John (Box 8.)
    - 1940
      - General (Folder 1)
      - April-May (Folder 2)
      - June (Folder 3)
      - July (Folder 4)
      - August-September (Folder 5)
    - 1941 (Folder 9.)
      - October-December (Folder 6)
      - January (Folder 1)
      - February (Folder 2)
      - March-April (Folder 3)
  - Heyl, Ernst (Folder 4)
  - Hynes, John (Folder 5)
  - Ilmetson (Norway) (Box 10., Folder 1)
  - MacDonald, William C. (Folder 2)
  - Poni and Paul Super (Budapest) (Folder 3)
  - Redfern, Gilbert
    - 1940
      - January-July (Folder 4)
      - August-December (Folder 5)
    - 1941 (Folder 6)
  - Shaler, Millard (Box 11., Folder 1)
  - Stephens, Dorsey [Zora]
    - 1940 (Folder 2)
  - Stephens, Dorsey [Zora] (Contd.)
    - 1941
      - January-April (Folder 3)
      - May-December (Folder 4)
  - Wilson, Randolph C. (Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1939-1947. (Box 12.-33.)
  Letters sent and received by the Commission for Polish Relief office. Includes correspondence with individuals, Local Committees, Polish societies in United States, organizations, consulates and embassies. Includes some other types of material. Arranged alphabetically by subject
  - General, 1940-1945
    - A-C (Box 12.)
    - D-G (Box 13.)
    - H-L (Box 14.)
    - M-P (Box 15.)
    - Q-S (Box 16.)
    - T-Z (Box 17.)
  - Individuals, 1940-1943 (Box 18.)
    - Adams, Stacy, 1940-1941 (Folder 1)
    - Agar, William M. (Folder 2)
    - Allen, Richard F., 1942 (Folder 3)
    - Beckelman, M. W., 1941 (Folder 4)
    - Biddle, Anthony D., 1940 (Folder 5)
    - Brener, Mina, 1942-1943 (Folder 6)
    - Brown, James W.
      - 1940 (Folder 7)
      - 1941 (Folder 8)
    - Brown, Milton, 1941 (Folder 9)
    - Cassel, Barry W., 1941 (Folder 10)
    - Castle, William R.
      - 1940 (Folder 11)
      - 1941 (Folder 12)
    - Cevey, Paul Ernest, 1941 (Folder 13)
    - Ciechanowska, Marie, 1941 (Folder 14)
    - Churchill, Winston, 1941 (Folder 15)
    - Cudahy, John, 1940 (Folder 16)
    - Darnall, John P. (Box 19.)
      - 1940 (Folder 1)
      - 1941 (Folder 2)
    - De Stoop, John, 1941-1942 (Folder 3)
    - Donovan, William J.
      - 1940 (Folder 4)
      - 1941 (Folder 5)
    - DuBois, Arthur Wood, 1940-1941 (Folder 6)
    - Frese, Herman B.
      - General
        - 1940 (Folder 7)
        - 1941 (Folder 8)
      - Reports (Folder 9)
  - Individuals (Contd.)
    - Frisse, Hans, 1941 (Folder 10)
    - Gamble, Arthur, 1940 (Folder 11)
    - Goldstein, Isidor, 1942-1943, 1947 (Box 20., Folder 1)
    - Goudvis, Theodore L., 1941, 1944 (Folder 2)
    - Gregg, John P., 1940-1941 (Folder 3)
    - Grove, William R., 1940-1941 (Folder 4)
    - Hartigan, John
      - Broadcasts, 1940 (Folder 5)
      - Correspondence
        - General
          - 1940
            - January-June (Folder 6)
            - July-December (Folder 7)
          - 1941 (Box 21., Folder 1)
        - Personal (Folder 2)
      - Report on trip to Poland, 1940 October 29-November 3 (Folder 3)
    - Heyl, Ernst, 1940 (Folder 4-5)
    - Horner, Charles F., 1941 (Folder 6)
    - Humphrey, Grace, 1941 (Folder 7)
    - Hynes, John, 1940 (Box 22.)
      - January (Folder 1)
      - February-March (Folder 2)
      - April-August (Folder 3)
      - September-December (Folder 4)
    - Kwapiszewski, Michael, 1941-1942 (Box 23., Folder 1)
    - Lehman, M. C., 1941-1943 (Folder 2)
    - MacAlarney, Robert E., 1941 (Folder 3)
    - MacDonald, William C.
      - General (Folder 4)
      - 1940 (Folder 5)
      - 1941 (Folder 6)
    - Majewski, Tomasz, 1941 (Folder 7)
    - Moen, Lara, 1941 (Folder 8)
    - Paderewski, Ignacy, 1940-1941 (Folder 9)
    - Rajchman, Ludwik, 1940-1941 (Folder 10)
    - Redfern, Gilbert
      - 1940
        - January-April (Folder 11)
        - May-September (Box 24., Folder 1)
        - October-December (Folder 2)
      - 1941 (Folder 3)
    - Richmond, Raymond, S., 1941 (Folder 4)
    - Rieber, Torkild, Captain, 1940 (Folder 5)
    - Ronikier, Adam, Count, 1945 (Folder 6)
    - Ropp, Stephan, 1941 (Folder 7)
  - Individuals (Contd.)
    - Segal, Simon (Folder 8)
    - Shaler, Millard, 1940-1942 (Folder 9)
    - Smith, James V., 1940-1944 (Folder 10)
    - Shattuck, Edwin P., 1940 (Box 25., Folder 1)
    - Sparrow, Edward, 1941 (Folder 2)
    - Spielrein, Jan (Folder 3)
    - Stephens, Dorsey
      - Correspondence
        - 1940 (Folder 4)
        - 1941 (Folder 5)
        - 1942 (Folder 6)
      - Personal papers (Folder 7)
    - Super, Paul
      - Correspondence, 1939-1941 (Folder 8)
      - Publications. Pamphlets about history of Poland (Folder 9)
      - Reports of the Polish Y.M.C.A. on its activities in Europe, 1941
        - First report, February (Folder 10)
        - Second report, March (Folder 11)
        - Third report, May (Folder 12)
    - Szoszkies, Henry, 1941 (Folder 13)
    - Topping, Tom, 1941 (Folder 14)
    - Tresidder, Donald B. (Folder 15)
    - Wilson, Randolph C. (Box 26.)
      - Correspondence
        - 1940 (Folder 1)
        - 1941 (Folder 2)
      - Report of relief activities in Europe, 1940 October 31 (Folder 3)
    - Zbudowski, Helen (Folder 4)
  - Local Committees, 1940
    - Belmont, Massachusetts (Folder 5)
    - Boston, Massachusetts. Includes Massachusetts mailing list (Folder 6)
    - Chicago, Illinois (Folder 7)
    - Cleveland, Ohio (Folder 8)
    - Hartford, Connecticut (Folder 9)
    - Hollywood, California (Folder 10)
    - Houston, Texas (Folder 11)
    - Idaho State Committee (Folder 12)
    - New Haven, Connecticut (Box 27., Folder 1)
    - New Jersey State Committee (Folder 2)
    - New York Committee. Contains partial list of Committee members (Folder 3)
    - Philadelphia, Pennsylvania (Folder 4)
    - Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania (Folder 5)
    - Poughkeepsie, New York (Folder 6)
    - Princeton, New Jersey. Includes statement of receipts and disbursements (Folder 7)
    - San Fernandino, California (Folder 8)
    - San Francisco, California (Folder 9)
    - South Amboy, New Jersey (Folder 10)
    - Syracuse, New York
      - List of persons present at meeting on 1940 January 17 for the purpose of forming a Committee for Polish Relief (Folder 11)
      - Report regarding the Formation of a Local Committee in Syracuse, New York, 1940 January 19 (Folder 12)
    - Utica, New York. Report regarding the formation of a Local Committee in Utica, New York, 1940 January 19 (Folder 13)
    - Washington, D.C. (Folder 14)
  - Organizations, consulates, and embassies, 1939-1947
    - Allied Relief Fund (Folder 15)
    - American Express Company. Foreign Remittance Department (Folder 16)
    - American Friends of Polish Democracy (Folder 17)
    - American Friends Service Committee
      - 1939 (Folder 18)
      - 1940 (Folder 19)
    - American Jewish Joint Distribution Committee (Box 28.)
      - 1941 (Folder 20)
      - 1940 (Folder 1)
      - 1941 (Folder 2)
    - American Red Cross
      - 1940 (Folder 3)
      - 1941-1942 (Folder 4)
    - Amtorg Trading Corporation, 1940 (Folder 5)
    - Bermuda. Imperial Censor, 1941 (Folder 6)
    - Brazilian Committee for Polish Relief (Folder 7)
    - Central Bureau for Registered Addresses (Folder 8)
    - Committee of Mercy (Folder 9)
    - Finnish Relief Fund (Folder 10)
    - German Red Cross (Folder 11)
    - Germany. Auswartiges Amt (Folder 12)
    - Germany. Botschaft (United States) (Box 29.)
      - 1940 (Folder 1)
      - 1941 (Folder 2)
    - Germany. Konsulat (New York) (Folder 3)
    - Great Britain. Consulate (New York)
      - 1940 (Folder 4)
      - 1941 (Folder 5)
    - Great Britain. Embassy (United States)
      - 1940 (Folder 6)
      - 1941 (Folder 7)
    - Huisking and Company, re codliver oil purchases (Folder 8)
    - Industrial Mercantile Corporation (Folder 9)
    - International Red Cross (Folder 10)
    - Kosciuszko Foundation
      - 1940 (Folder 11)
      - 1941 (Folder 12)
    - Mennonite Central Committee (American Mennonite Agency for Foreign Relief) (Folder 13)
    - National Catholic Welfare Conference (Folder 14)
    - National Committee on Food for Five Democracies
      - General (Folder 15)
      - Press release, 1941 March (Folder 16)
    - National Industrial Conference Board. Reports, 1941 (Box 30., Folder 1)
    - National Information Bureau (Folder 2)
    - Paderewski Fund for Polish Relief (Folder 3)
    - Paderewski Testimonial Fund
      - General (Folder 4)
      - Correspondence re fundraising needs (Folder 5)
    - Polish Central Relief Committee (Folder 6)
    - Polish Relief Fund, London (Folder 7)
    - Polish Women's Relief Committee (Folder 8)
    - Rada Polonii Amerykanskiej (Polish-American Council)
      - 1940
        - January-July (Folder 9)
        - August-December (Folder 10)
      - 1941 (Box 31., Folder 1)
    - Scottish Relief for Polish Prisoners (Folder 2)
    - Shuttuck, Bangs and Davis Corporation Company, 1941-1947 (Folder 3)
    - United States. Department of Agriculture
      - General (Folder 4)
      - Reports (Folder 5)
    - United States. Department of State
      - General. List of registrants (Folder 6)
      - 1939 (Folder 7)
      - 1940 (Box 32., Folder 1)
      - 1941 (Folder 2)
    - United States. Department of Treasury (Folder 3)
    - United States. Embassy (Germany) (Folder 4)
    - Polish societies, 1940-1941 (Box 33.)
    - Y.M.C.A. (Folder 5)
    - American
      - California (Folder 1)
      - Connecticut (Folder 2)
      - Iowa (Folder 3)
      - Illinois (Folder 4)
      - New Jersey (Folder 5)
      - New York (Folder 6)
      - Massachusetts (Folder 7)
      - Michigan (Folder 8)
      - Minnesota (Folder 9)
      - Ohio (Folder 10)
      - Oregon (Folder 11)
      - Pennsylvania (Folder 12)
      - Rhode Island (Folder 13)
      - Washington (Folder 14)
      - Wisconsin (Folder 15)
    - Foreign (Folder 16)
- Membership File, 1939-1947. (Box 33.-41.)
  File relating to directors and officers. Telegrams, letters, lists, memoranda, reports, minutes of meetings, statistical data and other records arranged alphabetically by names of directors and officers
  - General
    - Correspondence (Folder 17)
    - Form letters (Folder 18)
    - Letters of thanks (Folder 19)
    - Membership lists. See OFFICE FILE/Lists/Directors and officers (Box 34., Folder 1)
    - Minutes of meeting
      - 1939 (Folder 2)
      - 1940 (Folder 3)
      - 1941 (Folder 4)
      - 1942-1947 (Folder 5)
  - Abel, Theodore, 1940-1941. Correspondence (Folder 6)
  - Cooper, Merian C., 1940. Correspondence (Folder 7)
  - Galpin, Perrin. Correspondence
    - 1940 (Folder 8)
    - 1941 (Folder 9)
  - Gibson, Hugh
    - Cables
      - 1940
        - April-May (Folder 10)
        - June-August (Box 35., Folder 1)
        - September-December (Folder 2)
      - 1941
        - January-February (Folder 3)
        - March-April (Folder 4)
        - May-December (Box 36., Folder 1)
    - Correspondence
      - 1940 (Folder 2-3)
      - 1941 (Folder 4-5)
  - Kellogg, Vernon, 1939-1940. Correspondence (Folder 6)
  - Krueger, J. W., Colonel, 1941. Correspondence (Box 37., Folder 1)
  - McCormick, Chauncey. Correspondence
    - 1940
      - January-March (Folder 2)